Guide to the Fagel Stern Papers TAM.091
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Fagel Stern Papers
1922-1983
TAM.091
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.25 linear feet (1 box)
Faygle Stern (c1904-1936) was a Polish Jewish communist active in the Jewish Section of the International Workers Order in New York. She came to the United States in 1921, and died in childbirth in January, 1936. The collection includes her diary, correspondence with her brother Abram Judah, a communist who lived in Havana and the USSR, and biographical material (reminiscence, sketch, obituary). The diary, notebooks, and most of the letters are in Yiddish.
Stern, Fagel, ca. 1904-1936
Provenance
Gift of Phyllis Stern (niece of Fagel Stern), 1990.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Faygle Stern (c1904-1936), was a Jewish communist active in the Jewish Section of the International Workers Order, primarily as a teacher in the Yiddish shule movement in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn, New York. She was born in Ostroleka (a.k.a. Ostrolenka), Poland, came to the United States in 1921, and died in childbirth in January, 1936.
Scope and Content Note
Contains her diary, maintained during her fatal pregnancy, in which personal and political concerns are co-mingled; two notebooks with comments on Jews, Zionism, and world affairs; letters from her brother Abram Judah, also a communist who lived in Havana before returning to the USSR, where he died in 1933; letters from her brother Beryl, who came to the U.S. from Ostrolenka in 1935, and letters from her brother Chiel, who remained in Poland. Also contains biographical material (reminiscence, sketch, obituary). Two photographs of Fagel Stern have been transferred to the Library's non-print collection. The diary, notebooks, and most of the letters are in Yiddish, and are arranged alphabetically.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author.
The files are grouped into one series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Separated Material
Two photographs of Fagel Stern have been transferred to the Library's non-print collection.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. Patrons must use photocopy.
International Workers Order. Jewish Section.; Stern, Fagel, ca. 1904-1936; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Diaries.; Jewish communists |z Cuba.; Jewish communists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Jewish teachers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Jews, Polish |z New York (State) |z New York.; Letters (correspondence); Notebooks.; Political activists |z New York (State) |z Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Zionism.
- Series I
  - Stern, Abram Judah (Idl) - Death., 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stern, Abram Judah (Idl) - ltrs from Cuba to Fagel Stern, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stern, Abram Judah (Idl) and Fagel Stern - Immigration to United States - Documents., 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stern, Beryl - ltrs to Fagel Stern., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Stern, Beryl - ltr from R.Saltzman, National Secretary, Jewish Section, International Workers Order., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stern, Chiel - ltrs to Fagel & Beryl Stern., 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stern, Fagel - Biographical materials., 1936-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stern, Fagel - Diary. July, 1935, January, 1936., 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stern, Fagel - letters to Abram and Beryl Stern., 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stern, Fagel - Political notebooks., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stern, Naftali (uncle of Fagel) - letter to Fagel Stern., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tante - letter to Fagel Stern., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)